So I told you that this assignment was
intentionally repetitive and one of the
reasons this was intentionally
repetitive was to show you the benefit
of a for loop. So let's look through
this code that we wrote for that
selection project. So we got their
letter grades.
Then we used this if statement to
convert one letter grade, two letter
grades, three letter grades, four letter
grades. Then once we were done, we added
them all up, divided them by four. Then
we used another if statement for their
GPA. And well, you can see already here
we're at 223 lines of code. Yes, some of
that is comments, but a lot of that is
code. And we could definitely simplify
this. Anytime that you find yourself
copying and pasting code, I want you to
ask yourself, could I do this as a loop?
Um, I'll come back to this question
again because there's two ways to handle
repetitive code that we learn in this
course. But the first one is loops. So
if you're doing something over and over
again, ask yourself, could this be a
loop? And in this case, this can be. So
we said, what is your letter grade for
class 1, 2, 3, and four? This is
repeated. We created four variables
here. That is repeated lines of code.
This if statement was repeated multiple
times and in fact each of them was
repeated four times. But what we've
learned is that we can have some code
that repeats multiple times and that
changes slightly. So let's do that. So
let's create our for loop. So four,
where do we want to start counting?
Well, in the last video I started
counting at one, but in general
computers start counting at zero. So
generally you want to start your
counters at zero. So I'll say let
counter equal zero semicolon counter is
less than four because it'll do 0 1 2
and 3 and that is four times and so the
loop will run four times. Um if we said
it's less than or equal to four then it
would do 0 1 2 3 4 and that's actually
five times. So we want it to run from
zero to almost four and we want it to go
up
by one each time. This will make it so
that the loop will run four times.
Well, one thing we want to do
is we want to take we want to run
multiple lines of code because we've got
those lines of code and this if
statement is definitely multiple lines
of code. So, we're going to use the
curly braces. And so, now whatever we
put in here will run four times.
I'm going to take this and I'm going to
hold the option or if you're on a
Windows, you can hold alt and hit the up
arrow to bring it into the for loop.
What this would do is it would take a
letter grade and it would ask the user
for a letter grade. And so, we'd say
letter grade one equals prompt, what was
your letter grade for class one? So
there's a small problem but this this is
hardcoded but we want it to adjust. So
the first time we ask we want it to be
one then we want it to be two then we
want it to be three then we want it to
be four. Well what we could do is we
could take advantage of this counter
which is already going up four times. So
um we could say let letter grade one
equal prompt and then we'll use back
tick. You could use concatenation. I
prefer formatted strings. So I'm going
to put another back tick here. And where
we put one, we'll put dollar sign curly
brace. And now we can put our counter.
So just going to highlight everything
else
and comment it out
by hitting control or command slash. And
we'll save this. Now if we go live,
we'll see what was your class grade for
class zero.
A a A. So you notice that did zero
through three, which is what we expected
because we put our counter at zero. One
way you can handle this is you can say
counter + 1. The reason this works is
we're not storing this anywhere. We
didn't say counter equals counter + one.
We just said counter + one. So we're
saying we're going to take whatever
counter happens to be and display
whatever it is plus one. So now this
will display 1 2 3 and four. Um now our
um variable name doesn't make a whole
lot of sense because this is no longer
just storing letter grade 1. The first
time this loop goes through it's storing
letter grade 1, but the next time it's
storing letter grade 2. So maybe it'd be
better to just call this variable letter
grade.
Well, once we did that, we gathered four
inputs and then we stored um and then we
set GPA to be zero. And maybe we'll do
that again. So, let's grab this line and
hold option or alt and hit the up arrow.
Oh, the up arrow, not the down arrow to
bring it up into your code. And we'll
say let GPA equal zero.
After we did that, we ran a conversion.
So, I'm going to grab this if statement
here.
Sorry,
banged the wrong key. Grab Oh my gosh.
We're going to grab this if statement
here
and then hold the option or alt key and
we're going to move it up
into our loop.
Okay, it is now in our loop and we're
going to uncomment it by hitting command
slash
Okay,
so we said if their letter grade is a um
we said letter grade one and in all of
these cases we don't want the one
because we've called this letter grade.
So we'll get rid of letter grade one and
if you hold the option key or the alt
key and click in multiple places you can
put your cursor in multiple places and
we'll delete that.
So if we save this, we are now saying
get a letter grade.
Um create a GPA for it and then set that
GPA based on what the letter grade is.
So at the bottom we could alert GPA.
So now if we go back to
here, it says, "What is your letter
grade for class one?" If we enter an A,
uh it says, "What is your letter grade
for class 2?" And actually I'm going to
hit cancel, cancel, cancel. And I'm
going to reload this because I don't
think it reloaded after the last time.
So, what is your letter grade for class
one? A. And then it tells us that is a
four. What is your letter grade for
class 2? B minus. It tells us that's a
2.7. So, it looks like our converter is
working and it's able to take in all
four letter grades.
So, let's come back over here. Um, and
we don't need this alert anymore.
we're able to get a prompt, convert them
all to letter grades. But what we
probably want to be doing is, if you
notice at the bottom of all of this,
after we did all of the letter grades,
um, we had to calculate the total GPA,
which was summing up each of the letter
grades and then dividing it by four. We
could do this step by step. And so
what we could do is we could create a
running variable that stores the total
GPA. So total GPA equals zero.
Then
we'd gather a GPA and then we'd add it
to that GPA. So we'd say total GPA
equals total GPA plus whatever the GPA
for this letter grade is. or if we want
to shorten this plus equals GPA
and that so what that does is it's the
same as summing up all of the GPA. So
instead of taking
um instead of taking GPA 1 and adding
GPA 2 and then GPA 3 and then GPA 4, we
just said
take the GPA and set it to whatever the
first one is and then add on the second,
then add on the third, and then add on
the fourth as you go through the loop.
And then you'll notice at the end we do
need to divide by four. So we're going
to come after the loop. So
the for loop is the yellow curly brace.
So all the way down to the next curly
brace and we'll say total GPA equals
total GPA / 4. Or if you want to use
compound assignment, you'd say divide
equals 4.
And that gives us the exact same GPA
that we got last time.
Now, all that's left once we've gotten
that GPA
is to do the last if statement,
calculating their total. And so, I am
just going to grab it with option and
the up arrow, and I'm going to bring it
up
a whole long ways. I probably should
have just cut pasted at this point. Oh
well, you live and you learn.
So, you bring it all the way up.
put it right under total GPA.
Uncomment it.
And if we scroll back down,
that was the last line of code that we
needed to run. Um,
so now if we look at our code, our for
loop code, it is lacking some comments,
but using a for loop from line 14 to
line 70 is all the code that's needed to
do the assignment that previously took
all the way to about line 223.
So, because we didn't have to repeat
those if statements, we only had to
write one if statement. And then we um
inside of the loop, instead of having to
write four different if statements, um
we only had to write one prompt instead
of four prompts. And we were still able
to accomplish the same result. And that
is the power of the for loop. If you see
yourself duplicating code over and over
and over, then maybe you should use a
loop that will allow you to write the
code once and run it multiple times. So,
we'll save this just to prove it works.
and we'll say, "What is your letter
grade for class one?" We'll do an A, an
A minus, a B, a B+,
and a B. And that gives us a GPA of 3.5.
Says, "Great job. Your consistent effort
is paying off. Keep challenging yourself
and building on this progress." And so,
in just in much, much less code, we were
able to write something that
accomplished the exact same thing. Um,
and we'll pick up more on this in the
next video.